SANEESH CHALI KACHIMPURATH

DATA ENGINEER | DATA SCIENCE

Phoenix, AZ · 602-635-0302

ck.saneesh@gmail.com · https://linkedin.com/in/datasaneesh

Dedicated and experienced Data Engineer with proven success managing large Relational and NoSQL databases. Expert in database design and data migration, SQL analytics and reporting, query performance tuning and Unix shell scripting. Passionate about solving business problems using Data Science and Machine Learning.

EXPERIENCE

2018 - PRESENT

ASSISTANT CONSULTANT, TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES

- Analyzed and identified complex data duplication in Oracle database by aggregating records using SQL analytic functions reducing need for complex queries resulting in 50% faster time-to-solution.
- Architected redesign of large DB2 LUW Relational database involving XML data into NoSQL Couchbase solution improving query performance by 25%.
- Partnered with business team to analyze complex data correction in SQL Server database, devised a simplified approach involving SQL joins thereby avoiding complex scripts and resulting in 40% reduction in turnaround time.
- Developed advanced UNIX script for data migration in DB2 LUW with automatic parallelism for large tables resulting in over 75% reduction in migration time.
- Implemented automation purge script in Oracle database to purge historical data with additional validations to ensure correct data purge and reduce maintenance time by 5+ hours per month.
- Enhanced performance of JSON query in Oracle database by creating JSON Index resulting in 90% faster query execution time.
- Built replication setup for high availability including Golden Gate for Oracle and Log Shipping for SQL Server databases.
- Performed database migrations for version upgrades of 10+ databases including Oracle, SQL Server, and Heterogeneous database migration from DB2 LUW to PostgreSQL.
- Conducted Couchbase training sessions for 12+ application developers on the architecture and operations of the Couchbase cluster.

2014 - 2018

I.T. ANALYST, TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES

- Enhanced performance of data modifications in Oracle database by implementing PL/SQL bulk processing of records resulting in 80% faster execution time.
- Learned new database technology PostgreSQL in few days to complete build of database schema resulting in 30% faster time-to-market, praised by client for efforts.
- Tuned performance of SQL queries and improving response times by 30% in production databases.
- Created data reports using SQL analytic functions in DB2 LUW and Oracle databases, involving complex query joins and aggregation.
- Prepared documentation on PostgreSQL basics as learning reference for team of 5+ members.
- Executed data modification change requests which involved data backup, data manipulation scripts, and validation of data changes.

2012 - 2014

SYSTEMS ENGINEER, TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES

- Designed and created database objects (Tables, Views, Stored Procedures) and performed optimization using partitioning and indexing.
- Prepared advanced SQL queries including joins and aggregation to implement the business functionality using stored procedures and functions.
- Monitored and increased capacity of databases as per growing table size.
- Setup maintenance jobs including database backup, database integrity checks, database statistics.

EDUCATION

2009

BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING IN ELECTRONICS & COMMUNICATION,

CMR INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

First Class with Distinction, 74%

CERTIFICATION

IBM DATA SCIENCE PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATE

Actionable Learnings: Extracting & manipulating data using SQL. Utilizing GitHub for version control, and collaboration. Using Python for data analysis, manipulation & visualization. Applying data preparation steps for ML including missing values, categorical variable encoding, feature scaling, feature selection & model validation. Applying Machine Learning algorithms for regression, classification, and clustering. Turning business problems into Data Science solutions.

SKILLS

- Databases Oracle, SQL Server, DB2 LUW, PostgreSQL, Couchbase
- Programming SQL, Python (Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, Scikit-learn, SciPy), R
- Visualization Tableau
- Machine Learning Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, Decision Trees, Clustering, Classification
- Tools Jupyter Notebook, GitHub, MS Office

INTERESTS

- Yoga
- Video Gaming
- Traveling
- Learning Languages